Guide to the Arleen Schloss Papers MSS.437
Fales Library and Special Collections
Arleen Schloss Papers
1950-2015
Fales Library and Special Collections
Schloss, Arleen
Rodney (Sur), Sur
MSS.437
111.5 Linear Feet in 64 manuscript boxes, 45 cassette boxes, 37 record cartons, 6 LP boxes, 5 flat boxes, 1 card box, and 5 flat files.
807 audiocassettes
428 VHS
386 Hi8
337 MiniDV
231 U-matic
72 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel
47 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
9 Betamax
7 1_Inch_Video_Reel
5 DAT
2 Half_Inch_Audio_Reel
2 Betacam_SP
2 16mm_film_reels
1 Super_8mm_Film_Reel
46.1 Gigabytes in 610 digital files
Arleen Schloss (born 1943) is a New York City based poet, visual, performance, video, and film artist. An influential figure in the Downtown New York scene, she is known for her interdisciplinary loft space, A's, as well as her involvement in Danceteria, The Storefront of Art and Architecture, and the No Se No Social Club at the Rivington School. The Arleen Schloss Papers (1950-2015) contain audiovisual recordings, ephemera, photographs, and planning documentation from Schloss' performances, event series, exhibitions, collaborations, and audio works; audiovisual recordings and production files of her film, video, and television works; visual and written works; and files related to her academic career and personal life.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Arleen Schloss' Soho apartment in two installments in 2015; the accession numbers associated with these donations include 2015.437.001 and 2015.437.002. In January 2016, an accretion was added to the collection; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2016.008. In August 2023 material was donated by Sur Rodney (Sur), and the accession number for this accretion is 2023.051. In January 2024 material was donated by Sur Rodney (Sur), and the accession number for this accretion is 2024.005.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into seven series, with Series I, II, III, and VI arranged into subseries. Series are arranged chronologically with materials of similar content types grouped together. The arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Performances and Exhibitions
Subseries I.A Performance Art Workshops
Subseries I.B A's
Subseries I.C Events by Date
Series II. Video and Film Works
Subseries II.A Windows of Chance / Change
Subseries II.B Art Around the Park
Subseries II.C Travel Footage
Subseries II.D Works by Date
Series III. Visual Art
Subseries III.A Works by Date
Subseries III.B Photographs
Series IV. Written Works
Series V. Academic Career
Series VI. Personal Files
Subseries VI.A Personal Files
Subseries VI.B Personal Recordings
Series VII. Audiovisual Recordings
Biographical Note
Arleen Schloss (born 1943) is a New York City based poet, visual, performance, video, and film artist. An influential figure in the Downtown New York scene, she is known for her interdisciplinary loft space, A's, as well as her involvement in Danceteria, The Storefront of Art and Architecture, and the No Se No Social Club at the Rivington School.
Schloss attended the Parsons School of Design from 1961-1964 and attained a Bachelors of Education from New York University in 1967. She taught art at New York public elementary schools from the 1960s-1990s. In her own words, her framework of "teaching the alphabet with sound poetics and improvised chance operations" was a source of inspiration for her art. In her early educational and artistic career, Schloss lived in a building with other artists, including Merce Cunningham and Ray Kelly, with whom she began to organize workshops and parties (Bowery Artist Tribute, The New Museum).
Circle K Ranch began in 1971 as weekly "performance parties" organized by Ray Kelly, Bill Dunas of the Ambrose Art Foundation, and Arleen Schloss. In 1978, Schloss and R.L. Seltzman organized Performance Art Workshops on Monday evenings. From this came A's on a regular weekly basis, often referred to as "Wednesdays at A's" and "Saturday Night at A's." This experimental space at Schloss' 330 Broome Street loft was open to local and international interdisciplinary artists interested in collaborating and working with live audiences. Early participants included Claire Fergusson, Joe Lewis, Kirsten Hawthorne, Jean Allen as Boo the Clown, Mania D, and Tod Jorgensen. The first band to play at A's was Grey, Jean-Michel Basquiat's band. Posters for A's events were also the result of artistic collaborations, and were exhibited across Europe including at the Vienna Biennale and Art Basel in Switzerland.
As she was hosting these parties and workshops throughout the 1970s and 1980s, Schloss also performed some of her most well-known works. These include Shot Dot Shot and A Shot Chance (The Kitchen, 1977), Its A at MoMA (The Museum of Modern Art, 1978), AAA (Robert Freidus Gallery, 1978), The Staten Island Ferry Diamond Jubilee in 1980, How She Sees It By Her (various venues in New York City and Montreal, 1982), Performance A-Z (Storefront for Art and Architecture, 1982), The Letterwoman Show (Shuttle Theatre, 1984), A.E. Bla Bla Bla (Ars Electronica, 1986), and Loveletters (The Museum of Modern Art, 1987).
During this time, Schloss toured around the world to present her work at festivals and galleries. Her trips included a European tour in the early 1980s with performances in London, Berlin, Munich, Düsseldorf, Amsterdam, and Brussels; a trip to Japan in 1987 to study language, characters, and sounds, which culminated in video exhibitions and "Peace on Earth," a light and sound environment piece; a trip to China in 1992 with Asian American artists, where she presented a media workshop at the Hong Kong Art Center and collaborated with the Peking Opera in Taiwan; a 1993 residency in Bremen, Germany, where she taught multimedia and fine arts at Hochschule für Künste; a trip to South Korea in 1997 to participate in the Nine Dragon Heads International Environment Art Festival and Symposium; and repeated trips to Linz, Austria throughout the 1980s and 1990s to participate in the Ars Electronica Festival.
Throughout the 1980s and 1990s, Schloss also ran a video production studio in her loft, Studio A, and produced several works of film and television. Schloss' films include 30 Seconds (1983), Glenn Branca Symphony No. 4 / Physics (1984), It's A Live Laser (1985), A National Geographic (1989), Sun Daze Away (circa 1988-1992), Art Around the Park (1990-1998), From Kepler 2 Cyberspace: Virtual Worlds / Digital Dreams (1993), and Windows of Chance / Change (circa 1998). Her television work includes ID / It's Dance (1987-1989) and the Nickelodeon series Eureeka's Castle (1989-1990).
In September 1980, Schloss began to produce A's Gallery (also called Salon A and Le Salon A), which presented visual works and installations every Saturday. Many shows were put together by guest curators and each exhibit presented a different theme. In the 1990s, A's ended its regular schedule and Schloss developed A's Wave, a web platform to host multimedia performances and interactive projects. Schloss described A's Wave as the "digital sibling" of A's, where she practiced "investigating decontextualization extracting the digital usages of language with society's use of the Alphabet" (Bowery Artist Tribute, The New Museum).
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
A's Events Flyers Collection (MSS 277)
Scope and Content
The Arleen Schloss Papers (1950-2015) contain audiovisual recordings, ephemera, photographs, and planning documentation from Schloss' performances, event series, exhibitions, collaborations, and audio works; audiovisual recordings and production files of her film, video, and television works; visual and written works; and files related to her academic career and personal life.
The bulk of these materials relate to Schloss' collaborative performance series – Performance Art Workshops, A's, A's Gallery, and A's Wave – as well as her solo performances, including Shot Dot Shot and A Shot Chance (The Kitchen, 1977), Its A at MoMA (The Museum of Modern Art, 1978), AAA (Robert Freidus Gallery, 1978), The Staten Island Ferry Diamond Jubilee in 1980, How She Sees It By Her (various venues in New York City and Montreal, 1982), Performance A-Z (Storefront for Art and Architecture, 1982), The Letterwoman Show (Shuttle Theatre, 1984), A.E. Bla Bla Bla (Ars Electronica, 1986), and Loveletters (The Museum of Modern Art, 1987). Some of the other artists included in this collection from Schloss' collaborations and produced events are Ray Kelly, Hedda Sterne, Tomiyo Sasaki, Claire Fergusson, Butch Morris, Kwok Mang Ho, Nam June Paik, Tom Luckey, Buster Cleveland, and E. F. Higgins.
Schloss' film, video, and television production work is represented in analog audiovisual, digital, and paper materials. Analog and digital audiovisual recordings include both masters and dubs of finished works, source materials such as interviews and event coverage, and recordings used in production such as graphics and credits. Paper production files include a wide variety of documentation, including photographs and video stills, graphics, grant proposals, project timelines, budgetary documents, production and licensing contracts, receipts and invoices, and ephemera from screenings and festivals. The collection also includes footage of Schloss' travels, as well as ephemera, marketing materials, and invoices related to Studio A, Schloss' video production studio that she ran out of her Soho loft.
This collection contains visual art, including photographs, xerox art, paintings, sketches, sketchbooks, sculptural pieces, and textiles created by Schloss; photographs of Schloss taken by other artists; materials used in the art creation process, such as mock-ups, research files on various materials, letterpress transfer sheets, and source images; and Mail Art sent to Schloss by other artists, including E. F. Higgins, Buster Cleveland, Alan Rand, and Kwok Mang Ho.
Arleen Schloss also produced written work, including the alphabet poetry that she often performed. This collection contains drafts and final versions of published pieces, as well as unpublished notes, prose, and poetry. Much of Schloss' poetry is held in dozens of notebooks that were created in the 1960s-1990s. Published books in this collection include A Black Cat, A Dialogue Between New York and Texas, Book 5, Words Tell, The Red Book, Words, and How She Sees It By Her, as well as anthologies and publications that Schloss contributed to.
This collection also documents Schloss' career as an educator, including audiovisual recordings of classes, workshops, and lectures; paper curricula and course notes; ephemera from events such as the Children Arts Carnival and A's Performance School; programs and agendas for professional conferences attended by Schloss, including Art and Science Collaborations (ASCI) and the International Symposium on Electronic Art (ISEA); and two films, A Day in the Life of PS 19 (1992) and Chance to Succeed (1993).
Materials related to Arleen Schloss' personal life include correspondence with friends and family; business cards, rolodex cards, and address labels; her stamp collection; documentation of her travels; personal recordings, including footage of holidays, musical mixtapes given to her by friends, and recordings of memorial services; publicity, press, and interviews about Schloss' life and career; and documents related to Schloss' Broome Street loft.
Appraisal
In June 2024, 6 linear feet of paper materials were deaccessioned, including personal photographs and correspondence, sensitive health and financial documents, duplicate materials, and materials outside the scope of the collection. 145 audiovisual and digital media items containing personal, commercial, and class recordings were also deaccessioned.
In July 2025, 1 VHS was deaccessioned due to duplicative content.
Conditions Governing Access
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Restricted materials are notated as such in the record's title. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections with specific questions regarding access to such records. All other materials are open to researchers.
Alternative spaces (Arts facilities); SoHo (New York, N.Y.); Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York; Performance artists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Multimedia (Art).; Posters.; Color slides.; Journals.; Sketchbooks.; Promotional materials; Audiotapes.; Videocassettes.; Films.; American poetry -- 21st century; Film festivals.; Digital art; Computer art.; Video art -- United States.; Schloss, Arleen; Rodney (Sur), Sur; Cage, John; Storefront Gallery for Art and Architecture; Paik, Nam June, 1932-2006; Kwok, Mang Ho; Branca, Glenn, 1948-2018; Kitchen Center for Video, Music, Dance, Performance, Film, and Literature (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Performances and Exhibitions, 1960-2013; 82.4 Linear Feet in 44 cassette boxes, 33 record cartons, 12 manuscript boxes, 5 LP boxes, 5 flat files, and 4 flat boxes; 665 audiocassettes; 202 Hi8; 170 VHS; 137 MiniDV; 78 U-matic; 58 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel; 29 Half_Inch_Video_Reel; 4 Betamax; 2 DAT; 2 Half_Inch_Video_Reel; 1 1_Inch_Video_Reel; 1 16mm_film_reels; 1 Super_8mm_Film_Reel; 28.6 Gigabytes in 301 digital files
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Performances and Exhibitions (1960-2013) includes audiovisual recordings, ephemera, photographs, and planning documentation from Schloss' performances, event series, exhibitions, collaborations, audio works, and radio broadcasts. This series includes extensive documentation of Schloss' collaborative event series, including Performance Art Workshops, A's, A's Gallery, and A's Wave. It also includes recordings and documentation for Schloss' other performances, including Shot Dot Shot and A Shot Chance (The Kitchen, 1977), Its A at MoMA (The Museum of Modern Art, 1978), AAA (Robert Freidus Gallery, 1978), The Staten Island Ferry Diamond Jubilee in 1980, How She Sees It By Her (various venues in New York City and Montreal, 1982), Performance A-Z (Storefront for Art and Architecture, 1982), The Letterwoman Show (Shuttle Theatre, 1984), A.E. Bla Bla Bla (Ars Electronica, 1986), and Loveletters (The Museum of Modern Art, 1987). Some of the other artists included in this series from Schloss' collaborations and produced events are Ray Kelly, Hedda Sterne, Tomiyo Sasaki, Claire Fergusson, Butch Morris, Kwok Mang Ho, Nam June Paik, Tom Luckey, Buster Cleveland, and E. F. Higgins.
  Arrangement
  Series I. Performances and Exhibitions is arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries I.A Performance Art Workshops Subseries I.B A's Subseries I.C Events by Date
  Wherever possible, file names for audiovisual recordings were taken directly from tape labels and edited minimally for accessibility. Tapes that include content from multiple works or events are titled "Compilation Tapes," followed by a list of content in the title or the Scope and Contents Note.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections with specific questions regarding access to such records.
  - Subseries I.A: Performance Art Workshops, 1979-1980
    This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    This subseries includes audio and video recordings of Arleen Schloss' Performance Art Workshop event series, as well as ephemera, performance notes, and press clippings.
    - Ephemera, notes, and press clippings, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Video, 1979 (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1943)
    - #1, February 12, 1979
      - Audio (Box 66, Audiocassette 437_0085)
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1956)
    - #2, February 19, 1979 (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0520)
      Label also reads: "Bob's piece, group sounds, Lance"
    - #3, February 26, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0518)
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1946)
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1950)
    - #4, circa March 5, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0519)
        Full label reads: "Lance's fiber, Barbara reading performance piece, Iris slides, Susan dancing; Lance singing and playing guitar, Ellie's reading piece, Margaret's painting, Lance's group piece"
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0531)
        Full label reads: "Beginning workshop pre-exercise, breathing, three of us on solo sound, end of solo voice, watching last week's tape, paper section"
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1952)
        Full label reads: "1 minute sounds, 2 auto pieces by Elie Bernstein and hears by Margaret / Arleen III, March 5"
    - #5, March 12, 1979 (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0510)
      Full label reads: "typewriter jazz, trio section with music, John's song, Barbara's interview, Allen's reading, Davide on sax, video of last week, Lance's piece with John"
    - #6, March 19, 1979
      - Audio (Box 157, Audiocassette 437_0533)
        Full label reads: "Part of last week's workshop, sound section and foot painting, Barbara interviewing John and Danny, Iris on harmonica, Maureen talking about silkscreens, Claire's piece, Lance and bum actor, Slides of kids, some of Dieter's piece, Kay on camera and rhythm box"
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        This item was cleaned by the Preservation department in 2025.
      - Video (Box 95, Minidv 437_1456)
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1948)
    - #7, March 26, 1979 (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0516)
      Full label reads: "Claire and Ellen reading on subway, walking to subway, inside station and getting on train, ride downtown, watching tapes at Dieter and Kay's"
    - Performance Art Workshop on Subway, March 26, 1979
      - Electronic Records, FA_MSS_437_ER_5
      - Kim and Arlene Newvicon (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1942)
      - Video (Box 96, Minidv 437_1485)
    - #8, April 2-8, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0523)
      - Leo and Ellen Bates Film Showing (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0524)
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1953)
        Label also reads: "Lance's tape #6 at PAW 3/19"
    - #9, April 9, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0529)
        Full label reads: "Lance's piece about his father, after workshop went to Tin Palace to hear King drum in 'Light' band"
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0530)
        Full label reads: "Iris and Lance jamming on flutes, piano rehearsal at Modern with spinning by Josh, vocals, Iris on flute, Ellie's tack, Dieter's tape of subway"
      - Video (Box 152, Half inch video reel 437_2417)
    - #10, circa April, 1979 (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0521)
      Full label reads: "Flute, Iris and Lance duet, Barbara interviews Lance, Arleen's piano piece, Ellie's bottles piece, Lance's piece, Claire's piece, Slides of R.M. started to show, light blown out"
    - #10 and #11, April, 1979 (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1951)
    - #11, April 23, 1979 (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0522)
      Full label reads: "Dieter showed car tape and portrait, Margaret's piece - "Body Parts," Bottles and Simon by Arleen, Iris flute, Maureen dance, Dieter - part of "I Forgot I Remember," we watch last week's tape, two people played Simon while Dieter taped"
    - Subway excerpt, "4 in 1 Composition", April 24-27, 1979 (Box 79, Audiocassette 437_0627)
      Full label reads: "Side A: Beginning - '4 twins - music and a little dialogue of Liaday +3, a (sic.) Subay excerpt + going up to siren's + dialogue / Side B: Dub of 4 in one comp. Maed for Peggy Harrer"
    - #12, April 30, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0509)
        Full label reads: "a short alphabet piece, Lance and Marg's piece, Marg's story, some chatting, Glenn Velez tamborine and chant, people talking with Kay about her piece"
      - Audio (Box 76, Audiocassette 437_0508)
        Full label reads: "Chatting, Marg's piece, vocals, Iris and Lance, piano piece, Kay chatting, Claire reading a personal piece, Barbara interviewing Lance about Andy Kaufman, Kay's piece"
      - Video (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1947)
    - #13, May 5-7, 1979
      - Audio (Box 76, Audiocassette 437_0505)
        Full label reads: "flute piece by Iris and Lance, movement piece by Susan, Ellie's piece, Tony's piece, Barbara interviewing Tony, and intro by Davide"
      - Audio (Box 76, Audiocassette 437_0506)
        Full label reads: "Dieter video, Marg's piece, Lance's piece, Claire's piece, and Kay's piece"
      - Lance's Party (Box 76, Audiocassette 437_0507)
        Full label reads: "End of Kay's piece, Glen Velez and Arleen Schloss closing, people's reactions; Lance's party on May 5th with band from Washington Square"
      - Tape #1 Warmup, Kim Halsey, Arlene Krebs (Box 145, Half inch video reel 437_1958)
        An alternative label reads: "Claire Fergusson 'Figure Drawings' June, 1974; 25 min; model: Laura Fomisano; run 5 minutes into tape and then begin pre-screening for 10 minute period"
    - #14, May 14, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0528)
        Full label reads: "Warmups, Video - Davide, Lance from last week, a bit of Claire's piece from tape, a bit of Kay's, word piece, Lance's farewell piece, Barbara asked Lance a question"
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0527)
        Full label reads: "Some chatting, Iris and Lance's flute piece again, Davide harmonica piece with Chuck Berry song, Iris played flute, workshop talk for next week, at Dieter with delay"
    - #15, May 21, 1979 (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0511)
      Full label reads: "video-audio decay, warmups, Arleen's vocals, music group event with delay and feedback, Marg's piece, Lance's crash"
    - #16, May 28, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0512)
        Full label reads: "Arleen's audio, group sounds, solo sounds, Iris flute, Barbara reads three letters"
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0513)
        Full label reads: "Kay's bottle piece, Peter reads six poems, Ellie slides"
    - "It's A at B", June 1, 1979 (Box 79, Audiocassette 437_0609)
    - #17, June 4, 1979
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0515)
        Full label reads: "Arleen on drums, King on drums with Iris on flute, King, Iris, and Arleen on vocals, visual works on the wall, Kay and Ellie doing blue face improv; at Ellie's gallery"
      - Audio (Box 77, Audiocassette 437_0514)